now that we have four possible States
for a 2-bit predictor there is an
interesting question of does it matter
in which state we start the predictor of
so with the one bit predictor we had to
start it in either zero or one state if
we start it in two not taken state zero
that means that if the branch is
not-taken we will start predicting
correctly right off the bat if we start
predicting zero but the branch is
actually mostly taken we will have a
single miss prediction before we start
doing taken for a two bit predictor
however the question is really should we
start in one of the strong conviction
States or should we start in one of the
weak prediction States if we start in a
strong state for example zero zero and
the actual decisions are not taken then
we will stay in that same strong state
and never have any miss predictions
however if we start in the strong state
zero zero but the branch tends to be
taken
we will mispredict ones move to the zero
one the weak not taken state miss
predict again and then start predicting
correctly so if we start in a strong
state and it's the correct strong state
we have no miss predictions if it's the
wrong strong state we have to miss
predictions if however we start in a
weak state such as zero one and we
started in the correct weak state we
will just move to the strong state and
still have all correct predictions so in
the case when we guessed right what
should be the dominant behavior in the
starting state we have perfect reduction
regardless of whether we start in a
stronger weak state however if we were
wrong about where to start and we start
in let's say zero one but now the branch
is mostly taken we will have one miss
prediction here and now we will be
moving to the weak taken state and start
having correct predictions from then on
so if we start in a weak state we don't
lose anything if we will right but we
gain one less miss prediction if we were
wrong about what should be the bias so
this argument me
that probably we should be starting in
the weak state pick one doesn't really
matter however there is a flip side to
it let's say that the branch is taken
not taken taken not taken and we start
in the strong state the branch is taken
so we move to the weak state then it's
not taken so we move back to the strong
state and so on
we mispredict here but we correctly
predicted here and here so half the time
we have mispredictions
if we started in the one one state we
would have a similar behavior we would
miss predict every other time but if we
start in the wrong weak state and have
the same behavior here if the branch is
taken and we have a weak not taken we
miss predict and we move to the weak
taken state now the branch is not-taken
so we miss predict again and move back
to the weak not taken state the branch
is taken again so we miss predict again
and we keep miss predicting like this so
as far as worst-case behavior on
alternating branch decisions is
concerned starting in a weak state runs
some more risk of having this worst-case
behavior of always means predicting
fortunately this is much more common
behavior than this so probably it's a
good idea to start in a weak taken state
because taken branches are slightly more
common than not taken but in reality as
you can see it doesn't really matter
much because if the branch is mostly
taken one misprediction initial is not
really gonna be very cost it to us
because from then on it's gonna behave
the same way regardless of what we
started off with so in reality although
it seems like it's a good idea to start
in the weak taken state in practice the
overall accuracy of the branch picture
is affected very little by what exactly
do we start off in so we might as well
just start in zero zero state because
that's the easiest state to initialize
in two